okay here we go we're gonna do uh
backtracking
[Music]
uh
gratitude meditation
and then we're gonna go deeper okay so
this meditation has two meditations
right ready here we go
let's start with 20 breaths okay
and once a day I'd like you to do this
if you
if you're not sure ask cat okay
so please take one uh piece of food
or in here at Diamond Mountain we've all
in the morning we all get a green drink
or do fresh juice in
pick pick something
a juice or some piece of bread or rice
or whatever
who brought it to your
home or to the temple here
and thank them
try to imagine what they look like
then imagine where they brought it from
maybe a store
and try to imagine this people working
to
put the food out on the shelves for you
they are working all day
hard work
somebody took your money
somebody made the money somebody made
the paper money somebody made the credit
card somebody did the work for the
programming
for the payment online
hundreds of people
maintaining that
somebody brought the vegetables or fruit
from the farm to the store
I used to do that work in a truck and in
college and uh
it's very difficult work
somebody harvested that
those vegetables or fruit somebody
picked them
before you package them extremely
difficult work
somebody watered the field somebody
fertilized it
somebody plouted
somebody cleared it
we we owed them already our time in our
body
they have a right to some of our time
they have some right to what we do with
our body
the thought to thank them
the thought that they have a right
to sum up my time
also has its history
and this is a second meditation that I'd
like you to do today
this idea
to think about
the idea that someone that other people
might have an equal right to some of my
time
how did that idea start
you know what's the
lineage for that idea so oh well
I heard it from the long room
and then I'd like you to trace mentally
not physically
the the train of thoughts
that led you
to this point in time mentally
your mind
is considering today
the possibility
that other people already have a right
to your time
that we already owe them
some of our time if if we respect the
idea of people's rights
everybody has certain
rights in this world
then those people already have a right
to some of your time because they are
feeding you
they are giving you their time
and they are making your clothes
and they are making your house
and where did this idea come from in the
first place
who said they have an equal right
why am I hearing this right now oh well
I heard about this long rim
okay and then you had a thought right
yeah I was thinking I'd like to
hear that chorus I'd I'd like to hear
more about that and then
what were you thinking before that oh I
was curious I was looking around
I feel like there's improvements I could
make
in my life I heard about this Buddhism
stuff and alarm Rim stuff and
where did that thought come from well I
I guess uh
when I was in college I I heard about
Buddhism I I wasn't
learning it but I heard about it
and I was thinking about it you know
what happened before that well I was
thinking to go to college
I was thinking to go there there then
what what happened
oh well that come from my family
uh when I was thinking about my mom and
dad used to say about going to college
and
and and then that was sort of an
extension of
my grade school times and and I remember
thinking
about history and about the rest of the
world in my grade school times I can
remember those thoughts
I can remember the thoughts of going to
the first classes in my school I can
remember
especially things that went wrong
in school and I remember how I felt and
and I remember being curious about the
books and
about people what they had to teach and
I remember
the first days before I was only not to
go to school
and I remember what it was like to be
with my mom or my dad my family and I
remember
things we talked about and thoughts I
had
tracing back my mental process I
remember
a day
in my crib
touching a blanket
and feeling how soft it was and being
attracted to the softness I I remember
thinking about the softness
so what I'd like you to do
is two different meditations today one
is
physically
uh pick something you ate something you
wore something you drink
a house that you stayed in
and trace it back
to the people who made the materials who
planted the
to the people who passed on the
knowledge of building houses for 50 000
years
them go back and find new excuses to
thank more people thinking is a very
healthy
happiness creating exercise okay
and then I want you to notice in a
second meditation today and by the way
that should be
your fresh time so those of you who've
done retreat
you know there's a prime time a day and
you know there's a dull time of day so
prime time
for me it's mid-morning uh
trace it back Trace back your thoughts
and see how far back you can go and if
you work hard
you can trace back to the
to the few years after you were born you
can trace back to
when you were an infant a baby
it's possible to trace your mind stream
back
and then eventually you can break
through
uh
the current life and go back into the
darkness of the mushroom places before
this birth
it's possible to trace
your thoughts go in a flow
never stop being aware
for all time you will be aware
you have a recording in your mind
of past life you just haven't tried to
access it so while you're working on
tracing back your house or your food or
your clothing
and being grateful
then as a deeper meditation when you
when you're feeling
fresh
Trace back your thoughts
and see if you can trace your thoughts
back
and that's a very very deep
meditation and it has big big uh impact
on being able to see emptiness
okay the exercise
of tracing your thoughts back
and you'll get better and better at it
it's the first day it's kind of clumsy
it's like trying to ride a bicycle
and then after a week
you should be much better at it and that
has
a lot of power
in being able to see emptiness directly
so we're gonna do two
different kinds of backtracking
meditations one is a gratitude backtrack
based on a a piece of fruit or or a
house
or a car and then the other one
is a parallel meditation
where you backtrack your thoughts
and try to see what thought came before
the last one you you can't trace back
every single song
but you can trace back
with gaps you know you can say oh I had
this thought
10 years ago and I had this thought 12
years ago and
and then if you
practice you can work back before this
law
and it's a lot of fun because you
you remember all the Dharma thoughts you
had
okay open your eyes
take a stretch
take a drink Timothy any announcements
or
see you tomorrow
6 a.m World Central Time
which is Bowie Arizona
and it's fun to be with you guys and
thank you for coming online I can see
your smiling beautiful faces
and uh thank you and especially thank
you Francisco and all the stuff
thank you for working so hard especially
translators
and we'll see you tomorrow at 6 00 A.M
movement